Guide to the John Marcum Papers M1726
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John Marcum papers
1945-2013
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Marcum, John A.
M1726
55 Linear Feet: (68 boxes, 7 map folders)
John Marcum was an Africanist scholar and political historian who published extensively on post-colonial southern Africa, especially Angola, Mozambique, and South Africa. Marcum was also involved with education and study abroad programs both in Africa and elsewhere.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Some audiovisual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy. Selected media have been transferred and are available digitally.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Marcum, 2009-2014. Accessions 2009-296, 2010-022, 2010-193, and 2014-105.
Biographical / Historical
John Arthur Marcum (1927-2013) was an Africanist scholar and UC Santa Cruz professor emeritus of politics. Marcum was part of a small but passionate group of activist-scholars who helped shape and chronicle American relations with Africa during the collapse of colonialism and the birth of independent Africa. His influence and associations extended from academics and policy makers in the West to emerging leaders of Africa’s pre-independence nationalist movements such as Eduardo Mondlane and Patrice Lumumba. Marcum met, interviewed, and corresponded with many important African political figures, including Kenneth Kaunda, Ahmed Sékou Touré, Agostinho Neto, Holden Roberto, and Jonas Savimbi. He was also deeply involved in efforts to end apartheid in South Africa for more than three decades.
Born in 1927 in San Jose and raised in Napa, California, Marcum earned a B.A. (1949) and Ph.D. (1955) from Stanford University and an M.A. from Columbia University (1951). While at Stanford, Marcum worked as teaching and research assistant in the Program on Overseas Development at the Hoover Institution. He first became involved in sub-Saharan Africa after receiving a Fulbright-Hayes scholarship and studying French colonial involvement in West Africa at the University of Paris, Institut d’Etudes Politiques (1952-1954). He later received a Ford Foundation fellowship to continue his studies and travel in Africa, and spent time in Nigeria through the Experiment in International living program, while also also beginning his teaching career at Colgate University. In 1958, Marcum attended the first All-African People's Conference in Ghana. During the 1960 presidential campaign he advised John F. Kennedy and traveled to the continent with former governor Averell Harriman at Kennedy’s behest. In 1961 he moved to Lincoln University, where he worked to create and then direct a training program for African students at the African Language & Area Center.
Marcum was one of the world’s foremost experts on Angola and Mozambique. He is widely credited with writing one of the the foremost accounts of the Angolan revolution in the two volumes The Angolan Revolution: The Anatomy of an Explosion (1950-1962) and The Angolan Revolution Volume II: Exile Politics and Guerrilla Warfare (1962-1976). When the war for independence broke out in Angola in 1961, Marcum (with the American Committee on Africa’s George Houser) traveled on foot for 800 miles behind enemy lines conducting interviews and distributing medicine. At the time of his death he was completing the final edits on a history of the Mozambican revolution based on his trove of original documents and interview notes dating back to the late 1950s.
Marcum began teaching at UC Santa Cruz prior to his official appointment in 1972, but in time became provost of the university’s Merrill College, served as UCSC academic vice chancellor, and led the University of California’s Education Abroad Program for seventeen years beginning in 1990.
Marcum was also a PBS television panelist, president of the African Studies Association, edited the journal Africa Today, testified in Congress, and conferred with the State Department and other policy offices. He was also active in the Council on Foreign Relations and the Center for Strategic and International Studies. He observed elections in Angola in 1992, and served on the board of the Human Rights Watch Africa Advisory Committee in 2010. John Marcum passed away in 2013 due to complications following cancer surgery. He was 86 years old.
Adapted from an obituary written by Marcum’s family.
Scope and Contents
John Marcum’s papers primarily date from the late 1950s through the mid-1980s. The collection is arranged with most series organized in alphabetical order, including files on various countries. Within the series, files have been organized chronologically or alphabetically, transcribing Marcum’s folder labels and for the most part retaining his original order. A few series consist of a single folder, but most contain several boxes. Marcum’s own writings have been separated into several series, but correspondence is for the most part incoming, with fewer outgoing drafts.
One large chronologically-arranged series (Series 7) serves as home to documents and publications of a more general nature and is related to Marcum’s professional life and colleagues. Among the latter are significant exchanges with Gerry Bender, Helen Kitchen, George Houser, Winifred Armstrong, Chester Crocker, Patricia Tsien, Gwendolen Carter, Marvin Wachman, and Yvonne Williams among many others. This series also covers relations between countries, as well as regional and transnational groups or movements. However, files on various countries’ relations with the United States, Europe, the Soviet Union, China and Cuba are located in their respective series.
By far the most in-depth coverage in the collection concerns the Portuguese Colonial Wars in Angola and Mozambique. There is little on related conflicts in Portuguese Guinea or Cape Verde, however, and relevant files are in the Angola series. Other countries heavily represented in the collection include South Africa, Rhodesia/Zambia, Togo, and the Congo. Outside of Africa, Marcum gathered information on the independence movement in New Caledonia. In terms of his role as a teacher, there are several syllabi and course packs, but relatively few files concerning his work in the University of California system. There is a good deal of material on African scholarship and study abroad arrangements, however.
Correspondence includes letters from students, academics, politicians, diplomats, government workers, NGOs, volunteers, foundations, activists, clergy, businesspeople, and others. Other files contain political tracts and other publications, clippings, transcripts, photographs, and many notes by Marcum. There are several reproductions of otherwise rare documents. Also, due to prior exposure to flooding, color copies were made of the more severe mold and water damaged papers.
Africa -- History -- 20th Century; Angola -- Politics and government -- 20th Century; Mozambique -- Politics and government -- 20th century; South Africa -- Politics and government -- 20th century; National liberation movements; Pan-Africanism -- History; Marcum, John A.; Marcum, John A.
- Series 1. Writing
  - undated (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - reviews by Marcum (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - 1951, 1957-1959 (Box 58, Folder 3)
  - 1960-1963 (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 58, Folder 5)
  - 1971-1977 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Phelps-Stokes Fund- Marcum paper, 1974 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - Newsday article, 1976 (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - statement, House Committtee on International Relations Subcommittee on International Resources, Food & Energy / Senate Committee on Foreign Relations Subcommittee on African Affairs, June 26, 1976 (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - 1979-1984 (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 59, Folder 7)
  - 1990-1995 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - miscellaneous typescripts, including (partial?) drafts of unpublished 1960 book (Box 61)
  - published books (not complete) (Box 61)
- Series 2. Writing, Angola & Mozambique
  Scope and Contents
  Some relevant notes and notebooks were filed in Series 3, Notebooks.
  - Angola book drafts (Box 60, Folders 2-3)
  - undated (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - 1962-1965 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - 1965-1969 (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 62, Folder 4)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 62, Folder 5)
  - 1975-1979 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - testimony & statements, Senate Foreign Relations Committee Subcommittee on African Affairs, June 16, 1975, February 4, 1976 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Meet The Press appearance and reactions, 1976 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - "Lessons of Angola," Foreign Affairs, April 1976 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - 1980-1983 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - 1988 (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - 1989-1998 (Box 64, Folder 3)
- Series 3. Notes, notebooks & planners
  - notebook, undated (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - diary, 1945-1950 (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - "North Africa - 1956" notebook (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Nigeria/Experiment in International Living notebooks 1-5, 1957 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    Some notebooks also labeled Ghana, Liberia; Dakar-AOF, France: Portugal
  - planner 1958, notes, circa 1958 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Fulbright notes, 1957-1959 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - notebook & notes, circa 1959 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - planners, 1960, 1961 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - notebooks, 1965 & circa 1965 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - "Trip to North Angola" notebook, 1962 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - notebook - Congo, etc., 1962 (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - planners, 1963, 1965 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - notebook & planner, 1967 (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - planner 1974-1975; notebook, after 1976; planner, 1979 (Box 51, Folder 8)
  - notes, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - "Trip to S. Africa + Angola + S.W.A." notebook, 1984 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - planners, 1987, 1989, 1990 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - planners, 1992, 1993, 1994 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - planners, 1995, 1996, 1997 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - planners, 1998, 1999, 2000 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - planner 2002; notebook, after 2004?; planner, 2006 (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - planners, 2009, 2010, 2013 (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - four sets of indexed notes (removed from boxes) (Box 53)
  - two sets of index cards - Angola & Mozambique (removed from boxes) (Box 54)
  - index cards - organizations, etc. (removed from box) (Box 55)
  - notes- PhD material? (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - notes- possibly PhD research (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - index cards A-J (removed from box) (Box 56, Folder 3)
- Series 4. Class syllabi and readings
  - undated, 1956-1971, 2008 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - 1988 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - 1989 (Box 65, Folders 3-4)
- Series 5. Bios/resumes/CVs (Box 57, Folders 3-4)
- Series 6. Marcum in articles, press releases, etc.
  - 1956-1969 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - 1972-1992 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - Marcum in articles & press releases re: Angola & Mozambique (Box 64, Folder 4)
- Series 7. Chronological files, 1956-2012
  - undated ephemera, notes, cards, clippings, etc. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - undated correspondence (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - North Africa trip, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Colgate International Relations Study Group, etc., 1956 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Experiment in International Living trip - Nigeria, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1957 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation Fellowship trip to French West & Equatorial Africa, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Notes on Ruth Schlachter Lectures, 1958, 1959 or 1960 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - interviews, francophone Africa, 1958, 1959 or 1960 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - 1958 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - 1959 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Colgate University, Crossroads Africa, etc., 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - 1960 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Harriman tour, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - correspondence, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - publications & clippings, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Casablanca, UIAS/UAS, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Conferences of Heads of African and Malagasy States, Monrovia 1961 & Lagos 1962 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Related Materials
    See also OCAM 1966-7 in French Africa series
  - Department of State Foreign Service Institute lectures, 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 1962 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - correspondence, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - publications & clippings, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 1964 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - radio, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 1965 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - interviews - Southern Africa, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 1966 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1967 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 1968 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 1969 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 1970 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - 1971 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 1972 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 1973 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - International Congress of Africanists (Addis Ababa), 1973 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 1974 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Ford Foundation consulting project, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 1975 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 1976 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 1977 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Workshop on Decolonization: African Lessons & Pacific Experience, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Includes Marcum paper
  - 1980-1984 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - 1987 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - 1987 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - IISS - University of Zimbabwe conference, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - 1990-1994 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Adolfo Obiang Biko/MONALIGE, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - 1997-2012 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Series 8. Angola, 1956-2012
  - ANC/Black Opposition, 1988-1989 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Angola News Briefs (Angola Peace Fund), 1988-1991 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Gerald J. Bender re: Angola (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - CONCP (Conference of Nationalist Organizations of the Portuguese Colonies/Conferência das Organizações Nacionalistas das Colónias Portuguesas), 1961-1964 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - CSIS (Center for Strategic and International Studies), 1984-1992 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Economy (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Election - IFES briefing book, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Election/IFES, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Election - photos, articles, reports, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Election 1992 - IFES report, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Thomas Gilchrist, 1964-1965 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - David Grenfell, 1961-1971 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    also Jim Grenfell
  - Gulf Oil, 1971-1984 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - George Houser/American Committee on Africa re: Angola (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Internal War, 1988-1989 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    Mostly clippings
  - Emanuel Kunzika (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - MPLA (Popular Movement for the Liberation of Angola/Movimento Popular de Libertação de Angola), 1960-1962 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - MPLA, 1965-1985 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Namibia - Angola Negotiation, 1988 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Namibia - Angola Settlement, 1988 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - OAU (Organization for African Unity/Organisation de l'unité africaine) (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - PAIGC/Barry Alsiny, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Political asylum case, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Project "Pierre", 1987-1988 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Protestants & Catholics, 1987-1988 (Box 19, Folders 7-8)
  - Holden Roberto/FNLA/COMIA/PDA (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Jonas Savimbi, 1962-1992 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - South Africa - Angola clippings, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Soviets - Angola (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Soviets/Cuba - Angola (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - students/UNEA (National Union of Angolan Students/União nacional dos estudantes de Angola), 1962-1971 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - United Nations/International (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - UNITA (National Union for the Total Independence of Angola/União Nacional para a Independência Total de Angola), 1966-1982 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - UNITA, 1983-1984 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - UNITA, 1985-1987 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - UNITA press pack, circa 1986 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - UNITA, 1988-1989 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - UNITA, 1990-1994 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - UNITA/Free Angola Information Service bulletins and press releases, 1990-1993 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - UNITA /Free Angola Information Service - Kwacha News, 1986-1991 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - United States - Angola, 1960-1972 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - United States - Angola, 1973-1979 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - United States - Angola, 1980-1993 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - United States-Angola Chamber of Commerce, 1990-1994 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - UPA (United People of Angola/União das Populações de Angola), 1956-1968 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - chronological files, 1960-1967 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - chronological files - correspondence folder marked "private", 1962-1964, 1967-1968 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - chronological files - personal surveys, 1962 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - chronological files, 1971-1980 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - chronological files, 1981-1985 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - chronological files, 1987-1989 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - chronological files, 1990-2012 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - chronological files, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - academic papers on Angola and Mozambique (Box 25)
- Series 9. China
  - 1959-1991 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - News from Hsinhua News Agency, 1966-1972 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Hsinhua Daily Bulletin - mimeograph copies, 1966 (Box 26, Folder 3)
- Series 10. Education
  Mostly about African students in United States, especially through Lincoln University’s African Center program, and some about schools in Africa, especially higher education in South Africa. Appeals from young African students are scattered throughout various series, but most are here.
  - undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - 1958-1961 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - 1962 (Box 26, Folders 6-7)
  - 1963 (Box 26, Folders 8-9)
  - 1964 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - 1965 (Box 26, Folders 11-12)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - 1983-1995 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Jose Kunzike scholarship, 1985-1988 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - USSALEP (U.S. - South Africa Leader Exchange Program), 1966, 1983-1991 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - SAEP (South Africa Education Program), 1983, 1990 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Derek Bok, South Africa trip, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - South Africa trip, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Association of African Universities reports, 1994 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - CSIS report on South African education, 1995 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Ford Foundation study on South African higher education, 1994-1995 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Ford/American Council on Education study on South African education, 1996-1997 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Hanson/Meyerson - International Challenges to American Colleges and Universities (American Council on Education 1995) (Box 28, Volume 4)
  - Totemeyer - The African University in a Divided Society [bound study inscribed to Marcum by author], 1984 (Box 28, Volume 5)
- Series 11. EEC (European Economic Community), 1952-2007
  Original box was also labeled “Euroafrique.” Most concern late 1950s-early 60s trade pacts and negotiations between African and European countries, including development and investment. Includes material from Lyon Colloque/Colloque de Lyon, Council of Europe/Conseil de l'Europe, Alliance Europe Afrique, and the American Committee on United Europe (with a 1959 Allan Hovey, Jr. document based on an interview with Marcum). Please note that many files in this series are water damaged.
  - Colloque International Sur La Decision Dans Les Organisations Europeenes, 1966 (Box 29, Folders 1-2)
    box was labeled: "2. Lyon Colloque, EEC-Decision-making"
  - EEC - Africa, undated, 1952-1958 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    box was labeled: "6. EEC - Africa"
  - EEC - Africa, 1959-1960 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - EEC - Africa, 1962-1966, 2007 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Council of Europe/Conseil de l'Europe, 1957-1966; Handle with care; file has received significant water damage (Box 30, Folder 2)
- Series 12. Free Trade Area, 1964-1965 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  The majority of the material concerns conferences of the Organization for West African Economic Cooperation and the countries of Sierra Leone, Liberia, Ivory Coast, and Guinea. Details include judicial convention, trade, payments, telecommunications, and cultural and transport agreements.
- Series 13. French Africa, 1958-1967
  This series was assembled by Marcum, but a few other relevant files have been added. Most of the material dates to before his interest in southern Africa emerged. Files primarily concern trade and other regional agreements among Francophone countries including Gambia, Senegal, Congo, Mali, Guinea, Mauritania, and Cote D'Ivoire.
  - L'Afrique Equatoriale Francaise, 1958 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - OCAM (Organisation Commune Africaine et Malgache), 1966-1967 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Conseil de l'Entente, 1959 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - trade agreements & other documents, reports, memoranda, notes, etc., 1950s-1960s (Box 31, Folders 5-6)
  - ATEC (Agence Transequatoriale Des Communications), 1959, 1966 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - publications, 1954, 1966 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Algeria (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Congo (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Dahomey (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Haute-Volta (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Ivory Coast - Assemblee Territoriale de la Cote D'Ivoire - Premiere Session Ordinaire, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Senegal - Gambia (Box 32)
  - Alioune Diop transcripts, 1960 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Original mimeographs are severely curled on one side.
- Series 14. Ghana (Box 30, Folder 4)
- Series 15. Liberia, 1952-1966
  - 1952-1959 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - 1962-1966 (Box 33, Folder 3)
- Series 16. Mozambique, 1959-2013
  - Ronald Chilcote (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Committee for a Free Mozambique (NY), 1970-1972 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - COREMO (Revolutionary Committee of Mozambique/Comité Revolucionário de Moçambique), 1964-1974 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - COREMO publications (Box 34, Folder 4)
    Valiant Hero; O Combatente; Voice of COREMO; COREMO Newsletter
  - Marcelino dos Santos (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Early Movements (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - FRELIMO (Mozambique Liberation Front/Frente de Libertação de Moçambique), 1962-1963 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - FRELIMO, 1964-1965 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - FRELIMO, 1966-1967 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - FRELIMO, 1968-1976 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - anti-FRELIMO pamphlet (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - LSM (Liberation Support Movement) FRELIMO pamphlets (Canada), 1975 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - FRELIMO - Report of the Central Committee, after 1982 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Mozambican Revolution (FRELIMO newsletter), 1964-1974 (Box 35, Folders 7-8)
  - Mozambican Revolution (New York edition), 1964-1965 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Adelino Gwambe (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Allen Isaacson (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - David J.M. Mabuna/UDENAMO (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Samora Machel (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Joseph C. Massinga (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Leo Milas (aka Seifu Milasi) (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Eduardo Mondlane, undated, 1961-1965 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Eduardo Mondlane, 1969-1999 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - MOLIMO (Mozambique Liberation Movement/Movimento de Libertação de Moçambique) - FUMO (Mozambique United Front/Frente Unida de Moçambique) (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Mozambique Institute/Janet Mondlane (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Miguel Artur Murupa (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Joao Jamisso Nhambiu (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - PCN (National Coalition Party/Partido de Coligação Nacional) (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - RENAMO/MNR (Mozambican National Resistance/Resistência Nacional Moçambicana), 1982-1984 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Herbert Shore (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Uria Simango (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Syracuse Seminar, 1965 (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - UDENAMO (National Democratic Union of Mozambique/União Democrática Nacional de Moçambique)/MANU (Mozambican African National Union) (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - UDENAMO 1963-1965 / COSERU (Secret Committee of Udenamo Restoration/Comitê Secreto de Restauração da UDENAMO) (Box 38, Folder 2)